Hal Clement Papers
Hal Clement Papers
1939-2001
Clement, Hal, 1922-2003
6 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, science fiction short story writer and novelist. Includes artwork, correspondence, typescript drafts, revisions, and manuscripts of articles, novels, short stories, and speeches.
148690
Biographical History
Harry Clement Stubbs (1922-2003), better known as Hal Clement, was an award-winning American science fiction author, writing primarily "hard" science fiction short stories and novels. He also painted under the name George Richard.
Born May 30, 1922 in Somerville, Massachusettes, Clement graduated from Harvard University in 1943 with a B.S. in astronomy, having published his first short story the year before, and from Boston University in 1947 with an M.A. in Education. Clement served with the 8th Air Force in World War II and flew 35 combat missions over Europe; after the war, he served in the United States Air Force Reserve and eventually retired with the rank of colonel. He taught chemistry and astronomy for many years at Milton Academy in Milton, Massachusetts. He and his wife Mary Elizabeth had three children.
Clement was named a Grand Master by the Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers of America (SFWA) in 1998, and in 1996 he retroactively received a 1946 Hugo Award for his short story "Uncommon Sense." The Hal Clement Award for Young Adults for Excellence in Children's Science Fiction Literature is presented in his memory each year at the World Science Fiction Convention (better known as Worldcon).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hal Clement Papers consists of artwork, correspondence, memorabilia, printed material and writings.
Artwork consists of a number of paintings of stars, planets, and other astronomical subject matter, ranging from large canvases to small matted pieces.
Correspondence contains letters from family, friends and colleagues. Of particular interest are two letters from editor John W. Campbell, in which he discusses challenges facing genre authors and the author/editor relationahips; a letter from Isaac Asimov, whose tone suggests they were good friends; and a letter from L. Sprague De Camp in which he talks about his current projects including a Conan novel.
Memorabilia includes, among other things, items from Clement's time in the military in Washington, DC and Albuquerque, New Mexico; awards from science fiction fans and conventions; a number of photographs and slides (most of which are unidentified); and an engagement calendar from 1956.
Printed material consists of clippings about Clement and others, and assorted maps and National Forest Service publications.
Writings contains drafts of both fiction and non-fiction, including novels, short stories, book reviews, and speeches. In a few cases there are notes, calculations, sketches and so on relating to a given project. Many of the drafts show annotations, corrections and edits.
Arrangement of the Collection
Generally alphabetical by type or title; within correspondence, items within each folder are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of science fiction and fantasy authors as well as an extensive collection of early science fiction and fantasy magazines and 'zines and a large book collection. Please refer to for a complete listing of manuscript collections; for more information on the magazines, 'zines, and books please contact the repository listed above.
Separated Material
Edition of Ice World and three-volume set, The Essential Hal Clement, have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; Literature -- American Fiction; Asimov, Isaac, 1920-1992.; Campbell, John W., Jr. (John Wood), 1910-1971.; Clement, Hal, 1922-2003.; De Camp, L. Sprague (Lyon Sprague), 1907-2000.; Simak, Clifford D., 1904-1988.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Science fiction, American.; 16mm (photographic film size); 35mm (photographic film size); 8mm (photographic film size); Filmstrips.; Color transparencies.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Negatives (photographs); Paintings (visual works); Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Correspondence from James Pawlak and all writings (except for four folders, identified in the collection), gift of Harry C. Stubbs, 1968, 1970.
All other material purchased, 2013. Dealer stated the material was acquired at an estate auction after the death of Mary Stubbs, Hal's widow.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Paintings, undated; 2 large canvases and a smaller canvas panel; 3 items (Oversize 1)
  - Paintings, undated; one small canvas panel, 2 matted pieces; 3 items (Oversize 2)
  - Paintings, undated; matted pieces; 3 items (Map-case 133)
- Correspondence
  - Asimov, Isaac, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Bernstein, Gary, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Boskone XXIX, 1992; includes list of paintings submitted to art show (Box 1)
  - Campbell, John W., 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Churches, 1951-1952; in Cambridge, Boston, and Washington, D.C. (Box 1)
  - De Camp, L. Sprague, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Friese, Dana L. (Vulcanian Enterprises), 1967; includes list of stars mentioned in Star Trek (Box 1)
  - Knight, Francis H. P., 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - MarCon, undated; includes list of paintings submitted to art show (Box 1)
  - Simak, Clifford, 1969; on letterhead of Minneapolis Tribune (Box 1)
  - Galaxy, 1965-1966; includes black and white photocopies of cover illustration by Clement (Box 1)
  - Hubbard, W. R. ("Niffie"), 1952 (Box 1)
  - Stubbs, H--- (father), 1952 (Box 1)
  - Stubbs, Mary (wife), 1952; undated (Box 1)
  - Tropicon X, XI, 1992-1993; includes list of paintings submitted to art show, blue ribbon for "Astronomical Original" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950; 1952,; 1967-1968 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Army Air Force, 1943-1944; programs from Harvard Valedictory Service for student leaving to enter the armed forces; program from graduation exercises for Basic-Advance Flying School (Box 1)
  - Award, BaltiCon 35, 2001; guest of honor plaque, stamped leather on wood (Oversize 3)
  - Award, Invisible Little Man, 1962; presented by The Elves, Gnomes and Little Men's Science Fiction, Chowder and Marching Society; 2 cast footprints mounted on wooden block (Oversize 3)
  - Award, RiverCon XXIII, 1998; Toastmaster award, glass horse mounted on wooden base (Oversize 3)
  - Boston University commencement, 1947; Clement appears on p. 21 (as Harry Clement Stubbs) as receiving an M.A. in Education (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Children's Science Book Awards, 1975-1986; certificates of appreciation for serving as judge, 4th through 15th; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Filmstrips for Luxview projector, 1950s; four short 16mm[?] filmstrips, ranging from 15 to 18 frames, copyright North American Intrument Co.; title frames identify them as "First Christmas," "City Mouse and Country Mouse," "3 Clowns and [picture of red nose]" and "Greetje Visits Her Grandma" (Box 1)
  - Military, 1950-1953; undated; most items from Sandia Base in Albuquerque, New Mexico, others from Andrews and Bolling Air Force Bases in Washington, D.C.; items include dog tag, list of Sandia personnel, Officers Mess schedules, B-52 information, "aural null procedures," etc. (Box 1)
  - New Mexico, 1952; general information relating to the state and particularly Albuquerque; maps, tourist information, receipts from moving, bank statements, etc. (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated; personal photographs of Clement and unidentified others; formats include color and black and white prints, safety negatives, small aluminum tube containing 16mm and 35mm rolls of color transparencies, 2 small boxes of Kodachrome slides and a number of loose slides (Oversize 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939; 1947,; 1950-1951,; undated; Boy Scout card, program from graduation exercises for Ridge Technical School, President's Report from Harvard, etc. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Boy Scout necktie, fountain pen, ruler, magnifying lens, camera adapter, assorted other small items (Oversize 3)
- Printed material
  - Clippings about Clement, 1943; 1952; biographical essay by Anthony More in Science-Fiction Advertiser; clipping with photo of Clement receiving Air Medal (Box 2)
  - Clippings about others, 1952; review of Arthur C. Clarke's The Exploration of Space from New York Times Book Review (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; maps, catalogs, National Forest Service publications, etc. (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - An effort of logic, 1967; drafts A, B; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - How blue is an x-ray?, undated; drafts A, B; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The one you can never do twice, 1970; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Working up a sweat, 1970; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - You have to care how much, 1970; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Books, Fiction
    - Close to critical, undated; draft 1 (Box 2)
    - Cycle of fire, undated; first draft (Box 2)
    - First flights to the moon (anthology, edited by Clement), 1969; draft A; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - First flights to the moon (anthology, edited by Clement), 1969; draft B; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Ice world, undated; typescript, unidentified (Box 3)
    - Mission of gravity, undated; notes; draft A; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Needle, undated; drafts A and B; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Ocean on top (alternate title: No words for it), 1967; drafts A and B; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Ranger boys in space, undated; drafts A and B; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Star light, 1969; notes; drafts A, B and C; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Star light, 1970; draft D (Box 5)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, undated; royalty statement for Needles; page counts for 12 novels; graphs, calculations, sketches, etc. (Box 5)
  - Books, non-fiction
    - [untitlted chapter for science textbook], undated (Box 5)
  - Book reviews
    - "View on Science Books" column for Horn Book, 1967-1969 (Box 5)
  - Short stories
    - Bulge, undated; notes; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Critical factor, 1953; drafts A, B and C; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Dust ray, 1956; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - The foundling stars (alternate title: Significant figure), 1965 (Box 5)
    - Mechanic, undated (Box 5)
    - Mistaken for granted, undated; drafts A and B; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - A question of guilt, 1967; drafts A and B (Box 5)
    - Sun spot, undated (Box 5)
    - [untitled, with Sam Merwin], circa 1956 (Box 5)
    - [untitled, begins "I was a little late..."], undated (Box 5)
    - [untitled, begins "Gentlemen!..."], undated (Box 5)
  - Speeches
    - Characterizing an alien, for the Washington Science Fiction Association, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Life spectra: Speculations on the physical and chemical nature of extraterrestrial life, for the AAAS, 1961; notes and graphs; ditto master (Box 5)